A Finding Aid to the Solon H. Borglum and Borglum Family Papers, 1864-2002, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Printed Material, 1879-2002, undated; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 9, 13-14
  - Newspaper, Decatur-Dekalb News, "Stone Mountain Dedication Special Edition", 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Oversized matrial from Box 9, Folder 41.
  - Publication, "Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Silvermine Guild of Artists", 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 44.
  - Publication, Historical Biography and Libretto of the Indian Congress, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 45.
  - Publication, La Defense De Verdun, 1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 46.
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Solon Borglum, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folders 49-50.
  - Sound Construction by Solon H. Borglum, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 52.
  - Sound Construction by Solon H. Borglum, unbound version, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 9, Folder 53.
  - Supplement to Sound Construction by Solon H. Borglum, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 54.
  - Supplement to Sound Construction by Solon Borglum, unbound version, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 14)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 9, Folder 55.
- Photographs, 1864-1986; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 2 Linear feet Box 9-13, MGP 1, MGP 3, OV 15-16
  Found here are family and personal photographs, and numerous photographs of artwork by Solon Borglum. The bulk of the family and personal photographs date from Solon's adult life and include images of Solon in various settings, such as formal portraits taken throughout his career, photographs of him with his artwork, as a student and teacher in sculpture class, in Paris during his military service, with his family and friends at his farm, Rocky Ranch, and of Solon and Emma at the Crow Creek Reservation. Also found are Borglum family portraits, individual portraits of many family members including Solon's brothers Gutzon and August, and his parents James and Ida, as well as group portraits of the whole family. This subseries also includes photographs of Emma, Monica, her daughter Gwynneth, and Emma's brother Paul Vignal and his wife. Other personal photographs in this series are images of Solon at ranches and as a Boy Scout troop leader, exteriors and interiors of his various studios and residences, photos from an exhibition at the Union League Club in New York, and other miscellaneous and unidentified portraits and snapshots.
  Photographs of Artwork include files on individual works of art by Solon Borglum, as well as files for his various types of artwork, such as animal sculptures, portrait busts, and monuments and installations. Many of the files may include images of the artwork at the studio, as well as being unveiled or installed in public. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title of work, followed by categories of artwork and artwork by others. Photographs in this subseries have not been digitized.
  The Photographs series is arranged into 3 subseries. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  8.1: Family and Personal Photographs, 1864-1986, undated
  8.2: Photographs of Artwork, 1895-1967, undated
  8.3: Negatives, Slides, and Transparencies, undated
  - Family and Personal Photographs, 1864-1986, undated; 8.1; Archival Resource Key
    This bulk of this series has been digitized.
    - Solon Borglum Portraits, circa 1899-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Solon Borglum Portraits, circa 1899-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Solon Borglum in Sculpture Class, 1895-1897, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Solon Borglum with Works of Art, circa 1896-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Solon Borglum with Works of Art, circa 1896-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Solon Borglum in the American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Solon Borglum in the American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Solon Borglum at the A. E. F. School of Fine Arts, 1918-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Solon Borglum's Funeral, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 65)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 9.
    - Solon Borglum with Friends and Family, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Borglum Family Portraits, 1864; 1883-1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Borglum Family Portraits, 1898-1904; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Solon Borglum and Family at Rocky Ranch, 1906-1929, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Solon Borglum and Family at Rocky Ranch, 1906-1929; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Solon Borglum and Family at Rocky Ranch, 1906-1929; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Solon Borglum and Family Dressed in Costume, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Photo Album, Solon Borglum Family, 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Photo Album, Monica Borglum Davies, 1910-1920, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - August Borglum and Family, 1896; 1904-1905; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - August Borglum and Family, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Gutzon Borglum, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Emma Borglum, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Monica Borglum Davies, circa 1904, 1986, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Gwynneth Davies Kelly, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Paul Vignal and Wife Elizabeth, circa 1890-circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Paul Vignal and Wife Elizabeth, circa 1890-circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Paul Vignal and Wife Elizabeth, circa 1890-circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Boy Scout Troop, circa 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Friends of Solon Borglum, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Ranches in California and Nebraska, circa 1883-1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Solon Borglum Residences, 1894-1908; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Solon Borglum Studios, 1908, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Native American and Crow Creek Reservation, circa 1899; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 24)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, F10
    - Native Americans and Crow Creek Reservation, circa 1899; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 25)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 10.
    - B.N.L. Co. Sawmill and Dam, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Stone Mountain, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 27)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 11.
    - Exhibition at Union League Club, New York City, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Animals, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Portraits, unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 30-31)
    - Miscellaneous, 1864-1909, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous, unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Solon Borglum's Funeral, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Oversized material digitized with Box 13, Folder 65.
    - Native Americans and Crow Creek Reservation, circa 1899; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Oversize material digitized with Box 10, Folders 24-25
    - Stone Mountain, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 27.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1895-1967, undated; 8.2; Archival Resource Key
    - "Aspiration", 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - "The Bells of History,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - "The Blizzard", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - "Boy With Fish" Fountain, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - "Bronchos", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - "Bronchos Frightened by Saddle,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - "Bucking Broncho", 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 40)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 12.
    - "Buffalo", 1900, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - "The Bull Fight", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - "Burial on the Plains", circa 1902, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 43)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 13.
    - "Command of God to Retreat", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - "The Cowboy at Rest", 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 45)
      Oversized material housed in OV 15.
    - "Dancing Horse", circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - General John B. Gordon Memorial, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Giles A. Smith Monument, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Grant's Memorial, Model, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - "The Heavens", 1915, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - "Horse Pawing a Dead Horse", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - "Indian Child Being Sent to School", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - "The Intelligent Broncho", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Jacob Leisler Monument, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Joseph A. Mower Monument, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - "Lassoing Wild Horses,", 1897, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - "The Last Roundup", circa 1902, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - "The Little Lady of the Dew" ("The Waters"), 1920, 1934, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - "Monica", circa 1909, 1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - "On the Border of Whiteman's Land", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - "One in a Thousand", circa 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 61)
    - "Our Slave", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - "Paul", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 63)
    - "The Pioneer", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - "The Prayer", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 65)
    - "Private Jones", 1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 66)
    - "Rough Rider, Bucky O'Neill Monument", circa 1906, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 67-68)
    - "Sioux Indian Buffalo Dance", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - "Snowdrift", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "The Spirit of Death", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "The Stampede of Wild Horses", 1899; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Steps Toward Civilization", 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "Tamed", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 14.
    - Truman J. Backus Memorial, 1909, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "Washington 1753", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - William Sody Smith Monument, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "Winter", circa 1898, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Animal Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Bell Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Details of Unidentified Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Drawings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Figure Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Horse and Person Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Models for Sculpture Projects, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Monuments and Installations, 1901, 1903, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Paintings, 1895, 1897, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Portrait Busts, 1905, 1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Wood Carvings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Sculptures, circa 1903, 1909, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 21)
      Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folders 15 and 16.
    - Photo Albums of Artwork, circa 1899, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 22-28)
    - Solon H. Borglum Memorial Window by D. Putnam Brinley, circa 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Artwork by Gutzon Borglum, 1904, 1907, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Artwork by Others, 1898, 1919, 1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Bucking Broncho", 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 40.
    - "Burial on the Plains", circa 1902, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 13)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 43.
    - "Tamed", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Oversized material from Box 11, Folder 5.
    - Miscellaneous Sculptures, 1909, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15)
      Oversized material from Box 11, Folder 21.
    - "The Cowboy at Rest", 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 45.
    - General John B. Gordon Memorial, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 47.
    - "The Pioneer", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 64.
    - "Rough Rider, Bucky O'Neill Monument", circa 1906, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folders 67-68.
    - "Sioux Indian Buffalo Dance", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 69.
    - "Snowdrift", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 11, Folder 1.
    - Models for Sculpture Projects, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 11, Folder 16.
    - Portrait Busts, 1905, 1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 15)
      Oversized material from Box 11, Folder 19.
    - Miscellaneous Sculptures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 16)
  - Negatives, Slides, and Transparencies, undated; 8.3; Archival Resource Key
    This series has not been digitized with the exception of the glass plate negatives.
    - Glass Plate Negatives, General John B. Gordon Memorial, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
      4 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 1
    - Glass Plate Negative of Portrait Bust, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
      1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 3
    - Negatives, Monica Borglum Davies, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Negative of Unidentified People, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Negatives of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Slides, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Transparencies of Solon Borglum Paintings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Glass Plate Negatives, Archival Resource Key; 4 Glass negatives (Box MGP 1)
    - Glass Plate Negatives, Archival Resource Key; 1 Glass negative (Box MGP 3)
- Artwork, 1890-1921, undated; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 12-13
  Artwork contains many sketches by Solon Borglum, such as figure sketches for some of his sculptural works and for his book Sound Construction, as well as sketches he made on tracing paper, mostly of architectural design elements. This series also contains Emma Borglum's drawings of jewelry designs and sketches by Gutzon Borglum, including a sketch of Solon, possibly drawn while they were working together in 1894. Also found are original etchings for Silvermine Group of Artists Exhibition Announcements, a large illuminated poem made for Solon and Emma at the time of their marriage by writer William Theodore Peters, a military cartoon, and other artwork by unidentified artists. The folder of miscellaneous artwork by others includes etchings by artists Robert Fulton Logan and Frank Sohn.
  - Solon Borglum, Figure Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 13, F16) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Solon Borglum, Tracing Paper Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 13, F17) (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Solon Borglum, Miscellaneous Sketches, circa 1890-circa 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Solon Borglum, Miscellaneous Sketches, circa 1890-circa 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Solon Borglum, Miscellaneous Sketches, circa 1890-circa 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Emma Borglum, Jewelry Designs, 1901, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Gutzon Borglum, Sketches, 1894, 1900, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - William Theodore Peters, "The Betrothal", 1898; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 19.
  - Silvermine Group of Artists, Etchings for Exhibition Announcements, 1913, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified Artist, Military Cartoon, circa 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 19)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 20.
  - Miscellaneous Artwork by Others, 1919, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Artwork by Others, 1919, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Artwork by Others, unidentified, 1919, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Solon Borglum, Figure Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 16)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 12, Folder 10.
  - Solon Borglum, Tracing Paper Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 12, Folder 11.
  - Solon Borglum, Miscellaneous Sketches, 1890-1891, 1919, 1921, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 12, Folders 12-14.
  - William Theodore Peters, "The Betrothal", 1898; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 12, Folder 17.
  - Unidentified Artist, Military Cartoon, circa 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 20)
    Oversized material from Box 12, Folder 19.